# ANA PAULA MENDES

# Senior Software Engineer | Consultant

\$\ +55 86 99549-8253

■ anapaula.ds.mendes@gmail.com

🔗 anapaulamendes.github.io 👂 Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

in /anapauladsmendes 🐶 /anapaulamendes Updated at: March, 2023

#### **ABOUT ME**

I'm a Master's Degree student in Computer Science with a line of research in Intelligent Computing at Universidade Federal do Piauí. I am currently working as a Senior Software Engineer and have experience as a Developer Consultant. My areas of expertise are in Software Development and Artificial Intelligence.

I have a huge passion for teaching and sharing knowledge as much as I can. I believe that information in the right hands has the power to move the world and offer better conditions for society. I am continually cultivating other women with tech mentorship. I love participating in the Python Brasil community since I co-founded PyLadies Teresina in 2016.

# WORK EXPERIENCE

#### **Senior Software Engineer**

Remote

Jusbrasil

January, 2023 - Ongoing

São Paulo, Brazil

Development and maintenance of API's with Business to Business solution.

Technologies used: FastAPI, Pydantic, Python, Docker, PostgreSQL, Kubernetes and Git.

### **Developer Consultant**

Remote

**Thoughtworks** 

📋 April, 2021 - January, 2023

Recife, Pernambuco, Brazil

Thoughtworks is a leading global technology consultancy that integrates strategy, design and software engineering to enable enterprises and technology disruptors across the globe to thrive as modern digital businesses.

# **EDUCATION**

#### Master of Science - MS, Computer Science

Line of Research: Intelligent Computing

Universidade Federal do Piauí - UFPI

**2023** - Ongoing

Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

# **Bachelor of Computer Science**

Universidade Federal do Piauí - UFPI

**2016 - 2022** 

Paresina, Piauí, Brazil

#### **Software Development Technician**

Instituto Federal de Ciência e Tecnologia do Piauí - IFPI

📋 2012 - 2016

Paresina, Piauí, Brazil

#### **Industrial Administrative Assistant Technician**

Serviço Nacional de Aprendizagem Industrial - SENAI

**2012 - 2014** 

🗣 Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

# **SKILLS**

Python Django Git Django Rest Framework

Ruby Rails MongoDB Artificial Intelligence

HTML CSS JavaScript FastAPI

Working with Agile Methodologies, Lean Inception, Communication, Effective Feedback, High Performance Teams, Pairing; different software architectures like Monolith, Microservices, Backend for Frontend (BFF), Event Driven Architecture, Function as a Service (FaaS) and Architecture Evolution; support to Legacy Projects; Clean Code, Cl and CD, Monitoring, Observability, Metrics, Documentation, Unit tests, Integration tests, Continuous Improvement.

Business: Streaming with Metadata Processing and Video Processing

Technologies used: Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Sinatra, Python, Flask, JavaScript, Redis, MongoDB, GitLab, Tsuru, Sentry, Grafrana, NewRelic, GCP, React, React Hooks, HTML, CSS, Docker, Kubernetes.

#### **Backend Developer**

Remote

Muvext

📋 November, 2020 - April, 2021

Aveiro, Portugal

Engaged with API projects. Participating in issues discussions, refactor, improving features and working in the implementation of new ones, fixing bugs, writing tests and automating tasks.

Technologies used: Django, Django Rest Framework, Python, Docker, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Linux, Celery and Git

#### **Undergraduate Student Researcher**

Awarded Research at Seminários Integrados da UFPI 2020 🜟 1st place - Biotecnologia, Recursos Naturais e Tecnologia da Saúde 🜟

# CNPq - Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico

🗎 August, 2019 - August, 2020

♥ Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Project: Machine Learning Algorithm Tests for Nephropathology Diagnostic Inference

Application of data analysis and data mining for the discovery of patterns for the inference of diagnoses in nephropathology and the use of machine learning to build a web and mobile automated diagnostic tool for medical assistance.

Technologies used: Jupyter, J48, Python, Machine Learning, Data Mining, Data Analysis, Java, Weka and CSV.

#### **Full Stack Developer**

Remote

Quiploy

📋 October, 2018 - October, 2020

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Development of software for clinics (SaaS). Engaged with many company projects (backend, frontend, scripts, crawler). Participated in issues discussions, improved features and worked in the implementation of new ones, fixed bugs, writed tests and automated tasks.

Vim	Linux	REST		Docker	
Scraping	Weka	ì	Crawler		Tests
PostgreSQL	Pydar	ntic	Kubernetes		

#### LANGUAGES

#### **English**

Intermediate

#### **Portuguese**

**Native** 

# **VOLUNTEERING / TALKS / WORKSHOPS**

# Co-founder / Co-organizer

#### **PyLadies Teresina**

- June, 2016 July, 2018
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil
  - ★ Organized the 1st Teresina Women's Programming Marathon;
- ★ Organized the 1st Django Girls Teresina, 2017;
- ★ Organized technical workshops on Introduction to Programming with Python;
- ★ Mentor of Django Girls Belo Horizonte 2017;
- ★ Mentor of Django Girls Teresina 2018;
- ★ Mentor of Django Girls Teresina 2019;
- ★ Mentor of Django Girls Teresina 2022;
- ★ Keynote / Mentor of Django Girls Parnaíba 2022.

# Organizer / Member

#### **Teresina Hacker Clube**

- 📋 June, 2016 June, 2020
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil
- ★ Organized meetings, events, workshops.

# Organizer / Member

# **Python User Group - Piauí**

- 📋 July, 2016 June, 2020
- Teresina, Piauí, Brazil
  - ★ Organized meetings, events, workshops.

### **Invitations and Personal Initiatives**

- ★ Taught the Computational Thinking with Python Workshop EDIFPI (Encontro de Informática Piauiense) 2016;
- ★ Speaker: Computational Thinking for Engineers III Seminário de Engenharia Mecânica/UFPI 2016;
- ★ Speaker: Women in Science and Technology Software Freedom Day/Piauí 2016;
- ★ Monitor: Object Oriented Programming Computer Science/UFPI - 2017;
- ★ Speaker: Python Brasil 2017 Começando com Python: Aprendendo para ensinar, a melhor forma de programar!, 2017;

Technologies used: Django, Django Rest Framework, Python, JavaScript, Bootstrap, Zurb Foundation, Docker, Caddy, PostgreSQL, Vim, Linux, Screen, Axios, Celery, HTML, CSS, Git.

# Maintainer / Tech Lead

Open Source project

**Colaboradados** 

February, 2019 - September, 2020

Brazil

It is a collaborative initiative that seeks to gather, demonstrate, investigate and monitor access to information and open data in Brazil. Developing new features and fixing bugs. Responsible for refactoring and reviewing code. Managing the development team. Pointing and discussing the appropriate technologies for the project. Responsible for the project infrastructure.

Technologies used: Python, Twitter API, Jekyll, Git, Ruby, Github, Docker, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Django, REST.

# **Undergraduate Student Researcher**

CNPq - Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico

📋 August, 2017 - August, 2018

Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Project: Application of Fuzzy Logic for Automatic Identification of Immunogenic Epitopes in Epitopic Reactivity Analysis

Studied data analysis and data mining for the field of organ transplantation and developed an algorithm with J48 decision tree for the automatic identification of reactive epitopes with great accuracy in an organ transplant.

Technologies used: Java, Weka and CSV.

#### Freelancer - Web Scraping

**Upwork** 

February, 2018 - April, 2018

Wrote scripts with Selenium for automating processes like authentication, scraping content from a specific site, browsing between pages, and downloading files.

Technologies used: Python, Selenium, HTML, CSS, JavaScript.

#### **Administrative Assistant**

Eletrobras Distribuição Piauí

August, 2012 - August, 2014

Teresina, Piauí, Brazil

Worked through the Jovem Aprendiz Legal project, an initiative of the Federal Government. Gave administrative assistance to journalists in the Department of Communication and Institutional Relations.

Skills developed: Interpersonal relationships, teamwork, organization, responsibility, proactivity, entrepreneurship, business knowledge.

- ★ Speaker: Python Nordeste 2018 Algoritmo Genético com Python - 'Fruto do acaso ou de um processo evolutivo?!', 2018;
- ★ Speaker: Python Brasil 2018 Algoritmo Genético com Python - 'Fruto do acaso ou de um processo evolutivo?!', 2018;
- ★ Mentor of Python Workshop for Teachers Universidade Federal do Piauí - 2019;
- ★ Mentor of Python Workshop for Mechanical Engineers - Universidade Federal do Piauí - 2019;
- ★ Mentor and Organizer of Women's Programming Mentorship - Ana no Terminal - 2019;
- ★ Mentor of Django Workshop for Teachers -Universidade Federal do Piauí - 2019;
- ★ Speaker at Cerveja com Dados Teresina #01 with talk: Colaboradados: o veículo colaborativo sobre transparência e open data no Brasil - 2019;
- ★ Speaker: Talking about my career Faculdade iCEV 2019:
- ★ Speaker: Talking about my career Faculdade CEUPI -2019;
- ★ Speaker: Colaboradados o veículo colaborativo sobre transparência e open data no Brasil - Acontece no CT/UFPI - 2019;
- ★ Mentor of Python Workshop Faculdade CEUPI -2019.
- ★ Speaker: Oportunidades, conquistas e experiências na tecnologia PyLadies Parnaíba [Live], 2020.
- ★ Speaker: Python Brasil 2020 <u>Dados categóricos em</u> árvore de decisão utilizando libs Python, 2020.
- ★ Keynote: Python Nordeste 2020/2021 <u>Diversidade e inclusão fora das lideranças: um discurso vazio</u>, 2021
- ★ Speaker: Python Brasil, 2021 <u>Desbravando HTTP com</u> http.server.
- ★ Keynote: Django Girls Parnaíba 2022.
- ★ Speaker: Mulher Tech Sim Senhor, João Pessoa, 2023 Desbravando HTTP com http.server.

#### **PROJECTS**

# **Ana no Terminal**

A personal initiative to share knowledge about technology, teach programming and create projects that help society in Portuguese.

https://github.com/ananoterminal

https://www.youtube.com/c/ananoterminal